Guide to the Julio Elizalde Papers [Guía a los escritos de Julio Elizalde], 1973-2007 LATINAMER.2013.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Julio Elizalde Papers [Julio Elizalde Escritos]
1972-2007
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Elizalde, Julio
LATINAMER.2013.01
10 Linear Feet
The collection primarily consists of political analyses by Julio Elizalde written between 1972 and 2007. These writings heavily focus on current events of the time, specifically regarding U.S. foreign relations. The collection also contains personal accounts from Elizalde himself, in which he claims supposed ties to the government. La colección se compone principalmente de análisis políticos de Julio Elizalde escritos entre 1972 y 2007. Estos escritos se centran en los acontecimientos actuales de la época, específicamente en lo que respecta a las relaciones exteriores de USA. La colección también contiene relatos personales del propio Elizalde, en los que afirma supuestos vínculos con el gobierno.
The collection consist of 20 acid-free archival storage boxes with the letter-size writings organized chronologically by years. The materials are typewritten in Spanish and the majority are dated and signed. The papers are legible and in good condition. La colección consta en 20 cajas para archivos, libres de ácido, con los escritos tamaño carta organizados cronológicamente por años. Los materiales están mecanografiados, escritos en español y la mayoría están fechados y firmados. Los papeles son legibles y en buen estado.
Access Restrictions [Restricciones de Acceso]
No restrictions.Sin restricciones.
Acquisition Information [Información de Adquisición]
Gift of Marietta Worrell, daughter of Julio Elzialde, on August 22, 2013. Donación de Marietta Worrell, hija de Julio Elizalde, el 22 de agosto de 2013.
Arrangement [Arreglo]
The collection is arranged in chronological order.La colección está ordenada cronológicamente.
Biography [Biografía]
Julio Elizalde was born in Matanzas, Cuba, on January 9, 1926 as the youngest of four children. His family eventually moved to Havana where Elizalde graduated from an independent journalism school. Elizalde wrote for several papers and magazines in Cuba, including Bohemia. Days after the declaration of the Cuban Revolution, Elizalde and his brother, Leopoldo Elizalde (a lawyer from Havana University), sought asylum in Mexico. Julio Elizalde ultimately relocated to New York City in the 1970s. Julio Elizalde had two daughters, the oldest being born in Cuba and the youngest in the United States. He separated from his wife and lived with his companion of over forty-five years, a woman of French descent named Monet Holec, whom he eventually married. The couple resided on West End Avenue in New York City.
Elizalde considered the New York Public Library as his "working place." It is here that Elizalde wrote the majority of the documents contained in this collection. In New York, his articles were published by Patria, a small, political, anti-Castro/Revolution publication edited in Miami in the late 60's and early 70's, as well as in Diario de las Américas, the oldest newspaper published in Spanish for the Latin American community, founded in 1953.
Elizalde passed away on October 27, 2007.
Julio Elizalde nació en Matanzas, Cuba, el 9 de enero de 1926 siendo el menor de cuatro hermanos. Su familia eventualmente se mudó a La Habana donde Elizalde se graduó en una escuela de periodismo independiente. Elizalde escribió para varios periódicos y revistas en Cuba, incluyendo "Bohemia". Días después de la declaración de la Revolución Cubana, Elizalde y su hermano, Leopoldo Elizalde (un abogado de la Universidad de La Habana), buscaron asilo en México. Julio Elizalde finalmente se trasladó a la ciudad de Nueva York en la década de 1970. Julio Elizalde tuvo dos hijas, la mayor nacida en Cuba y la menor en Estados Unidos. Se separó de su esposa y luego se volvió a casar. Su segunda esposa fue Monet Holec. Elizalde y Monet residían en West End Avenue en la ciudad de Nueva York
Elizalde consideraba la Biblioteca Pública de Nueva York como su "lugar de trabajo". Es aquí donde Elizalde escribió la mayoría de los documentos contenidos en esta colección. En Nueva York, sus artículos fueron publicados por "Patria", una pequeña Publicación Política contra de la Revolución Cubana, editada en Miami a finales de los 60 y principios de los 70, así como en el "Diario de las Américas," el periódico más antiguo publicado en español para la comunidad latinoamericana, fundado en 1953.
Elizalde falleció el 27 de octubre de 2007.
Scope and Content Notes [Notas de Alcance y Contenido]
Most of this collection is centered on political/philosophical memorandums concerning the following subjects: The tumultuous relationship shared between the Global North superpowers and the developing countries of the Global South; the documentation and rebuttal of covert CIA; critiques of the Western military–industrial complex and its propensity for war, and a generalized lineal recording of the geopolitical interactions between Cuba, the former Soviet Union, and the United States during the peak of the Cold War (all from an anti-Castro perspective). The correspondence includes letters between Elizalde and a diverse group of individuals including:
Marta Fernández Miranda de Batista: First Lady of Cuba from 1952 until 1959. She was the second wife of Cuban President Fulgencio Batista, who was overthrown by Fidel Castro in the 1959 Cuban Revolution, which forced the couple to flee permanently into exile.
Salvador Diaz-Verson: A famous anti-Batista crime reporter/journalist who was exiled from Cuba. Returning to Cuba on the eve of the triumph of the revolution, he took an active part in the reorganization of the government.
Alejandro Agustín Lanusse: the de-facto president of the Argentine Republic between March 22, 1971, and May 25, 1973, during the military dictatorship of the country called the "Argentine Revolution".
Sergio Santelices: The director of El Diario-La Prensa, which was one of the largest Spanish-language dailies during the early 1970s.
Manuel F. Benítez Rodríguez: The specifics of Rodríguez's exact identity are unknown, but it is clear through the letters exchanged between him and Elizalde that he had direct access to Fulgencio Batista (even after the former president lost power of Cuba). Rodríguez likely acted as a liaison between Elizalde and powerful political elites in Cuba who still secretly aligned with the Batista regime even after Castro took rule.
Manuel Álvarez Bravo: A Celebrated Mexican photographer and artist.
There is no indication that some of his writings were published in Cuban Newspapers/Journals. It is likely that Elizalde's long-form essays and monographs were published in either Cuban-diasporic underground magazines (anti-Castro factions) or Western-backed publications who sought to propagandize his rhetoric. Even if these writings were never published, they provide a valuable insight into a perspective systematically eradicated by the Cuban state.
In his writings, Elizalde often prides himself on his ability to analyze political situations based on his vast knowledge of world history. It combines political events and the actions of world leaders with quotes from past events, referring to philosophers, thinkers, literary authors, famous composers. It also uses Greek mythology and ancient history to describe and illustrate the events of the world today. Some of the names in the documents include: Aristotle, Heraclitus, Cicero, Plato, Leibnitz, Nero, Hitler, Caligula, Machiavelli, Carter, Kennedy, Nixon, Gorbachev, Beethoven and Rousseau.
His analyses are addressed to various recipients throughout four decades including the Political Department of the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), the Defense Intelligence Agency (DIA), the Pentagon, and Charles E. Wilson, Chief Officer of the Plans and Policy Branch of the C.I.A. Elizalde also writes to General Dynamic Corp., Boeing Co., and McDonnell Corp., all of which he collectively refers to as the "three private institutions." Several series of works occur throughout the collection: At the Heights of World Conflict, Reflections, Decisive Hours, and The Hour of Truth.
La mayor parte de esta colección se centra en memorandos político/filosóficos sobre los siguientes temas: La tumultuosa relación compartida entre las superpotencias del Norte Global y los países en desarrollo del Sur Global; la documentación y refutación de operaciones encubiertas de la CIA; críticas al complejo industrial-militar occidental y su propensión a la guerra, y un registro lineal generalizado de las interacciones geopolíticas entre Cuba, la ex Unión Soviética y los Estados Unidos durante el apogeo de la Guerra Fría (todo desde una perspectiva anticastrista).
La correspondencia incluye cartas entre Elizalde y un grupo diverso de personas incluyendo:
Marta Fernández Miranda de Batista: Primera Dama de Cuba desde 1952 hasta 1959. Fue la segunda esposa del presidente cubano Fulgencio Batista, quien fue derrocado por Fidel Castro en la Revolución Cubana de 1959, lo que obligó a la pareja a huir definitivamente al exilio.
Salvador Diaz-Verson: un famoso reportero / periodista criminalista y anti-Batista, que fue exiliado de Cuba. De regreso a Cuba en vísperas del triunfo de la revolución, participó activamente en la reorganización del gobierno.
Alejandro Agustín Lanusse: presidente de facto de la República Argentina entre el 22 de marzo de 1971 y el 25 de mayo de 1973, durante la dictadura militar del país denominada "Revolución Argentina".
Sergio Santelices: director de "El Diario-La Prensa", que fue uno de los diarios en español más importantes de principios de la década de 1970.
Manuel F. Benítez Rodríguez: Se desconocen los detalles de la identidad exacta de Rodríguez, pero queda claro a través de las cartas intercambiadas entre él y Elizalde que tuvo acceso directo a Fulgencio Batista (incluso después de que el expresidente perdió el poder de Cuba). Rodríguez probablemente actuó como enlace entre Elizalde y las poderosas élites políticas en Cuba que todavía se alineaban en secreto con el régimen Batista incluso después de que Castro asumió el gobierno.
Manuel Álvarez Bravo: un célebre fotógrafo y artista mexicano.
No hay indicios de que algunos de sus escritos hayan sido publicados en Diarios / Revistas Cubanos. Es probable que los ensayos y monografías extensos de Elizalde se publicaran en revistas clandestinas de la diáspora cubana (facciones anticastristas) o publicaciones respaldadas por Occidente que buscaban propagar su retórica. Incluso si estos escritos nunca se publicaron, brindan una valiosa visión de una perspectiva erradicada sistemáticamente por el estado cubano.
En sus escritos, Elizalde a menudo se enorgullece de su capacidad para analizar situaciones políticas basándose en su vasto conocimiento de la historia mundial. Combina eventos políticos y acciones de líderes mundiales con citas de eventos pasados, refiriéndose a filósofos, pensadores, autores literarios, compositores famosos. También utiliza la mitología griega y la historia antigua para describir e ilustrar los eventos del mundo actual. Algunos de los nombres en los documentos incluyen: Aristóteles, Heráclito, Cicerón, Platón, Leibnitz, Nerón, Hitler, Calígula, Maquiavelo, Carter, Kennedy, Nixon, Gorbachov, Beethoven y Rousseau.
Sus análisis están dirigidos a varios destinatarios a lo largo de cuatro décadas, incluido el Departamento Político de la Oficina Federal de Investigaciones (FBI), la Agencia de Inteligencia de Defensa (DIA), el Pentágono y Charles E. Wilson, Director de la Rama de Planes y Políticas de la CIA. Elizalde también escribe a General Dynamic Corp., Boeing Co. y McDonnell Corp., a las cuales se refiere colectivamente como las "tres instituciones privadas". Varias series de sus trabajos ocurren a lo largo de la colección: En las alturas del conflicto mundial, Reflexiones, Horas decisivas y La hora de la verdad.
World politics; United States -- Foreign relations; International relations; Cuba -- Politics and government; Cuba; Elizalde, Julio
- Writings, 1972-2007; I.
  - Writings, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondencia de Manuel F. Benítez R. a Julio Elizalde [Correspondence from Manuel F. Benítez R. to Julio Elizalde], 9 de marzo, 1972 [March 9, 1972]; 1.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Sergio Santelices, Director de El Diario-La Prensa [Correspondence to Sergio Santelices, Director of El Diario-La Prensa], 8 de octubre, 1972 [October 8, 1972]; 2.; 1 page
    - Saludos a Mayo por Julio Elizalde [Greetings to May by Julio Elizalde], 1973 [1973]; 3.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Carlitos [Correspondence to Carlitos], 16 de marzo, 1973 [March 16, 1973]; 4.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Nanana [Correspondence to Nanana], 30 de marzo, 1973 [March 30, 1973]; 5.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia al General Alejandro Lanusse [Correspondence to General Alejandro Lanusse], 1 de abril, 1973 [April 1, 1973]; 6.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Avelino Rodríguez [Correspondence to Avelino Rodriguez], 16 de abril, 1973 [April 16, 1973]; 7.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 15 de agosto, 1973 [August 15, 1973]; 8.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Johnny Torres y Frank Lugoviña [Correspondence to Johnny Torres and Frank Lugovina], 24 de agosto, 1973 [August 24, 1973]; 9.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 26 de agosto, 1973 [August 26, 1973]; 10.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 31 de agosto, 1973 [August 31, 1973]; 11.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 5 de septiembre, 1973 [September 5, 1973]; 12.; 1 page
    - Nota Especial, Para: Sra. Marta, R.F. Miranda, R. Batista [Special Note, To: Mrs. Marta, R.F. Miranda, R. Batista], 5 de septiembre, 1973 [September 5, 1973]; 13.; 3 pages
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 16 de septiembre, 1973 [September 16, 1973]; 14.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 22 de septiembre, 1973 [September 22, 1973]; 15.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Orlando [Correspondence to Orlando], 14 de octubre, 1973 [October 14, 1973]; 16.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Marta [Correspondence to Marta], 4 de noviembre, 1973 [November 4, 1973]; 17.; 1 page
    - La seguridad norteamericana en peligro: Un estudio político especial, Para: Marta Fernández, Viuda de Batista [North American Security in Danger: A Special Political Study, To: Marta Fernández, Widow of Batista], 4 de noviembre, 1973 [November 4, 1973]; 18.; 4 pages
    - Correspondencia a Manolo [Correspondence to Manolo], 4 de diciembre, 1973 [December 4, 1973]; 19.; 1 page
  - Writings, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 21 de enero, 1974 [January 21, 1974]; 1.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Orlando [Correspondence to Orlando], 7 de marzo, 1974 [March 7, 1974]; 2.; 4 pages
    - Correspondencia a Carlos Navedo [Correspondence to Carlos Navedo], 12 de marzo, 1974 [March 12, 1974]; 3.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Jacobo [Correspondence to Jacobo], 21 de marzo, 1974 [March 21, 1974]; 4.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Abel [Correspondence to Abel], 27 de marzo, 1974 [March 27, 1974]; 5.; 3 pages
    - Correspondencia a Abel [Correspondence to Abel], 4 de abril, 1974 [April 4, 1974]; 6.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Dolores [Correspondence to Dolores], 16 de abril, 1974 [April 16, 1974]; 7.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Abel [Correspondence to Abel], 1 de mayo, 1974 [May 1, 1974]; 8.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Abel [Correspondence to Abel], 9 de mayo, 1974 [May 9, 1974]; 9.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 9 de mayo, 1974 [May 9, 1974]; 10.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 1 de junio, 1974 [June 1, 1974]; 11.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 17 de junio, 1974 [June 17, 1974]; 12.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 17 de agosto, 1974 [August 17, 1974]; 13.; 1 pages
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 11 de diciembre, 1974 [December 11, 1974]; 14.; 1 page
    - Colby en el Senado [Colby in the Senate], 1975 [1975]; 15.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Ana María [Correspondence to Ana María], 18 de enero, 1975 [January 18, 1975]; 16.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Kiko [Correspondence to Kiko], 27 de julio, 1975 [July 27, 1975]; 17.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 29 de septiembre, 1975 [September 29, 1975]; 18.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Kiko [Correspondence to Kiko], 26 de octubre, 1975 [October 26, 1975]; 19.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Manuel Álvarez, Director de Diagramación de Vanguardia [Correspondence to Manuel Álvarez, Director of Vanguard Design], 26 de octubre, 1975 [October 26, 1975]; 20.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 8 de diciembre, 1975 [December 8, 1975]; 21.; 2 pages
  - Writings, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pekín No Confía en U.S.A. [Beijing Does Not Trust in the U.S.A.], 1976 [1976]; 1.; 2 pages
    - En la muerte de Mao Tse-tung [On the Death of Mao Tse-tung], 1976 [1976]; 3.; 2 pages
    - U.R.S.S.: 1976 [U.S.S.R.: 1976], 1976 [1976]; 2.; 3 pages
    - El Kremlin [El Kremlin], 1976 [1976]; 4.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Salvador Diaz Versón [Correspondence to Salvador Diaz Verson], 7 de febrero, 1976 [February 7, 1976]; 5.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 23 de febrero, 1976 [February 23, 1976]; 6.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Emilio [Correspondence to Emilio], 3 de marzo, 1976 [March 3, 1976]; 7.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Salvador Díaz Versón [Correspondence to Salvador Diaz Verson], 6 de marzo, 1976 [March 6, 1976]; 8.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Salvador Díaz Versón [Correspondence to Salvador Diaz Verson], 27 de marzo, 1976 [March 27, 1976]; 9.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a la Sra. Amparo Villanueva [Correspondence to Mrs. Amparo Villanueva], 6 de abril, 1976 [April 6, 1976]; 10.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 21 de abril, 1976 [April 21, 1976]; 11.; 3 pages
    - La carta de Castro [Castro's Letter], Mayo, 1976 [May 1976]; 12.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 7 de mayo, 1976 [May 7, 1976]; 13.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 23 de mayo, 1976 [May 23, 1976]; 14.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 24 de mayo, 1976 [May 24, 1976]; 15.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 28 de mayo, 1976 [May 28, 1976]; 16.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 14 de julio, 1976 [July 14, 1976]; 17.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 26 de julio, 1976 [July 26, 1976]; 18.; 2 pages
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 7 de octubre, 1976 [October 7, 1976]; 19.; 3 pages
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 13 de octubre, 1976 [October 13, 1976]; 20.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Salvador [Correspondence to Salvador], 27 de octubre, 1976 [October 27, 1976]; 21.; 2 pages
  - Writings, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aclaración [Clarification], 1978 [1978]; 1.; 1 page
    - Memorándum: Las bases de la conspiración comunista en occidente son Washington y New York [Memorandum: The Bases of Communist Conspiracy in the West Are Washington and New York], 19 de septiembre, 1979 [September 19, 1979]; 2.; 4 pages
    - Nota: Ahora, más que nunca antes, urge una solución en el medio oriente [Note: Now, More Than Ever, There Urges A Solution in the Middle East], 18 de noviembre, 1979 [November 18, 1979]; 3.; 2 pages
    - Memorándum: Sin un pensamiento político que guíe a los Estados Unidos, las más modernas armas estratégicas son estériles e incapaces de ser vehículos para una labor histórica trascendente [Memorandum: Without a Political Thought That Guides the United States, The Most Modern Strategic Weapons Are Sterile and Incapable of Being Vehicles for a Historical Transcendent Labor], 2 de diciembre, 1979 [December 2, 1979]; 4.; 2 pages
    - Nota: Los pronunciamientos públicos del Coronel Muammar Qaddafi [Note: The Public Declarations of Coronel Muammar Qaddafi], 12 de diciembre, 1979 [December 12, 1979]; 5.; 2 pages
    - Memorándum: Un mensaje a las cabezas políticos de la Agencia Central de Inteligencia [Memorandum: A Message to the Political Heads of the Central Intelligence Agency], 13 de diciembre, 1979 [December 13, 1979]; 6.
    - Memorándum: La lección de Vietnam y el futuro de los Estados Unidos [Memorandum: The Lesson of Vietnam and the Future of the United States], 17 de diciembre, 1979 [December 17, 1979]; 7.; 3 pages
    - Nota: Visión objetiva de la situación en Irán [Note: Objective Vision of the Situation in Iran], 19 de diciembre, 1979 [December 19, 1979]; 8.; 2 pages
    - Nota: Insistencia en la importancia suprema que tienen las ideas [Note: Insistence on the Supreme Importance that the Ideas Have], 28 de diciembre, 1979 [December 28, 1979]; 9.; 2 pages
    - Memorándum: Un artículo deshonesto de Jack Anderson [Memorandum: A Dishonest Article of Jack Anderson], 31 de diciembre, 1979 [December 31, 1979]; 10.; 2 pages
  - Writings, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Nota: Necesidad urgente de una filosofía de Estado [Note: Urgent Necessity of a Philosophy of the State], 2 de enero, 1980 [January 2, 1980]; 1.; 1 page
    - Nota: El Viaje del Secretario de Defensa a China [Note: The Secretary of Defense's Visit to China], 4 de enero, 1980 [January 4, 1980]; 2.; 1 page
    - Correspondencia a Mr. Wilson [Correspondence to Mr. Wilson], 9 de enero, 1980 [January 9, 1980]; 3.; 2 pages
    - La traición al pueblo americano [Betrayal Against the American People], 13 de octubre, 1980 [October 13, 1980]; 4.; 3 pages
    - El pueblo americano está siendo conducido a la derrota [The American People Are Being Led to Defeat], 19 de octubre, 1980 [October 19, 1980]; 5.; 4 pages
    - Casete [Cassette], 2 de diciembre, 1980 [December 2, 1980]; 6.; 2 pages
  - Writings, February-June 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Casete: Las relaciones estados unidos-europa occidental [Cassette: United States-West European Relations], 9 de febrero, 1981 [February 9, 1981]; 1.; 3 pages
    - Nota: Nubes negras, muy negras sobre los Estados Unidos [Note: Black, Very Black Clouds Over the United States], 10 de marzo, 1981 [March 10, 1981]; 2.; 2 pages
    - Memorándum: La situación en centroamerica [Memorandum: The Situation in Central America], 10 de marzo, 1981 [March 10, 1981]; 3.; 2 pages
    - Nota: La división interna en los Estados Unidos [Note: The Internal Division in the United States], 18 de marzo, 1981 [March 18, 1981]; 4.; 3 pages
    - Compilación de abrazos a Mr. Wilson [Compilations of Hugs to Mr. Wilson], 18 de marzo, 1981 - 9 de febrero, 1984 [March 18, 1981 - February 9, 1984]; 5.; 22 pages
    - Un estudio político: La crisis de Polonia [A Political Study: The Crisis of Poland], 5 de abril, 1981 [April 5, 1981]; 6.; 5 pages
    - Memorándum: Reflexiones finales sobre el medio oriente [Memorandum: Final Reflections on the Middle East], 12 de abril, 1981 [April 12, 1981]; 7.; 4 pages
    - Nota: Polonia, Después del discurso de Brezhnev [Note: Poland, after Brezhnev's Speech], 12 de abril, 1981 [April 12, 1981]; 8.; 2 pages